[MUSIC]
[موسيقى]
So, let's see a little example we're going to go through by hand and
لذا، دعونا نرى مثالًا بسيطًا حيث سنقوم بشكل يدوي
show what the derivative would be for a particular parameter.
بإظهار ما يمكن أن تكون عليه مشتقة معلمة معينة.
We have a model and it says that so far at iteration t w0 is
لدينا نموذج وهو يشير إلى التكرار بالحرف t حيث W0 = 0،
equal to 0, w1 is equal to 1, and w2 equal to minus 2.
و W1 = 1 وW2 = -2.
This is our current estimate wt.
وهذا تقدير wt الحالي لدينا.
And the question is, how we're going to modify it?
والسؤال هو، كيف سنقوم بتعديله؟
How are we going to compute the derivative?
كيف سنقوم بحساب المشتقة؟
And we're going to compute the partial derivative of the likelihood function
وسنقوم بحساب المشتقة الجزئية للدالة الاحتمالية
with respect to the parameter w1.
فيما يتعلق بالمعلمة W1.
And the parameter w1 is going to multiply the first feature,
وستقوم المعلمة W1 بمضاعفة السمة الأولى،
which is h1 of x which, in our case, is number of awesomes.
وهي (h1(x والتي تمثل في حالتنا عدد الأشياء الرائعة.
So, what is the contribution that each one of these data points will have
فما القيمة التي ستكون لدى كل نقطة من نقاط البيانات هذه
to the derivative with the equation above.
بالنسبة للمشتقة بالمعادلة أعلاه.
That's what we're trying to do.
وهذا ما نحاول القيام به.
So if you look at the question above, for
لذا، فإذا نظرت إلى المعادلة في الأعلى،
each one of these we're going to make a prediction according to the current model
فسنقوم بإجراء تنبؤ لكل واحدة من تلك المعلمات وفقًا للنموذج الحالي
as to whether that data point is actually a plus one.
فيما إذا كانت نقطة البيانات تلك تساوي فعلًا القيمة +1.
So for the first one, which has two awesomes and one awful we get to
لذا، بالنسبة للنموذج الأول الذي لديه اثنين من الأشياء الرائعة وواحدة سيئة،
the tree label plus one, but our model only assigns 0.5 probability to it.
فإن العلامة الحقيقية هي +1، ولكن النموذج لدينا يمكنه فقط تعيين 0.5 كنسبة احتمالية.
So not perfect.
لذا، فهذا ليس مناسبًا.
What contribution does that have to the derivative?
ما القيمة لدى تلك المعلمة بالنسبة للمشتقة؟
Well, let's just go through the equation above.
حسنًا، دعونا ننتقل إلى المعادلة بالأعلى.
So, h1 of xi is the number on the left here, is two.
لذا، فإن (h1(xi هو الرقم الموجود على اليسار هنا ويساوي 2.
And it multiplies the difference between the indicator function.
وسيكون مضروبًا في الفرق بين دالة المؤشر.
Is this a positive example?
هل هذا مثال إيجابي؟
Yes, it is a positive example.
نعم، هو مثال إيجابي.
And, the probability that we get from data which is 0.5.
والاحتمالية التي نحصل عليها من البيانات والتي تساوي 0.5.
So the contribution here is 2 times (1-0.5) which is exactly equal to 1.
لذا، فإن القيمة هنا هي (0.5 - 1) مضروبة مرتين، والتي تساوي بالضبط 1.
Let's look at the next data point.
لنلقِ نظرة على نقطة البيانات التالية.
The next data point the h1 of x has value zero.
في نقطة البيانات التالية فإن (h1(x تساوي صفرًا.
So in this case w1 is not important to it, but now just let's go through.
لذا، فهذه الحالة فإن المعلمة W1 ليست مهمة بالنسبة لها، ولكن دعونا فقط نكمل الأمر.
This is multiplying the indicator, is this a positive example?
وستكون هذه القيمة مضروبة في المؤشر، هل هذا مثالًا إيجابيًا؟
In this case it's not, so it's zero minus the probability that the model signs for
فالإجابة لا في هذه الحالة، لذا، ستكون صفرًا مطروحًا من علامة هذا النموذج
this to be a positive label which in this case is 0.02,
حيث إن هذه علامة موجبة والتي ستكون في هذه الحالة 0.02،
and the total here contribution is going to be zero.
وستكون القيمة الإجمالية هنا هي صفر.
It's interesting for this particular data point, the model gets it extremely right,
إن الأمر مثير للاهتمام بالنسبة لنقطة البيانات هذه، حيث أن النموذج توصل إلى النتيجة الصحيحة تمامًا،
it says the probability's positive is very, very, very small, 0.02,
فهو يشير إلى أن نسبة إيجابية الاحتمالية صغيرة للغاية حيث تساوي 0.02،
which means it's very likely to be a negative example which in fact it is,
مما يعني أن هذا من المحتمل أن يكون مثالًا سلبيًا، وهو كذلك في الواقع،
it's two awfuls, zero awesomes.
فإن لدينا اثنين من الأشياء السيئة، ولاشيء رائع.
Now, let's look at the third example.
والآن، لنلقِ نظرة على المثال الثالث.
It's a bit of an unusual example.
وهو مثال غير عادي بعض الشيء.
It has three awesomes and three awfuls.
حيث أن لديه ثلاثة أشياء رائعة وثلاثة أشياء سيئة.
And it is actually a negative example, and
وهو في الواقع مثال سلبي،
the model thinks it is pretty likely to be a negative example, so
ويشير النموذج أنه من المحتمل جدًا أن يكون مثالًا سلبيًا،
it's 0.05 probability of being positive, so 95% chances of being negative.
فهو لديه نسبة احتمالية 0.05 بأن يكون إيجابيًا، لذا، فهناك فرصة بنسبة 95% أن يكون سلبيًا.
So once the contribution says to the derivative, okay so let's look at h1 of x,
لذا، فما القيمة لدى تلك المعلمة بالنسبة للمشتقة؟ حسنًا، دعونا نلقِ نظرة على (h1(x،
in this case is three.
والذي في هذه الحالة يساوي 3.
It multiplies the difference between the indicator
وسيكون مضروبًا في الفرق بين المؤشر
that there is a positive example.
الذي يشير إلى أن هذا مثالًا إيجابيًا.
So in this case it's not so it's zero.
والذي ليس في هذه الحالة، لذا سيكون صفرًا.
Minus the probability assigned to the positive example which is 0.05.
مطروحًا من الاحتمالية التي تم تعينها إلى المثال الإيجابي والتي تساوي 0.05.
If you multiply this together, you get minus 0.15, so
فإذا قمت بضرب كل هذا معًا، فستحصل على -0.15،
that's the contribution, contribution is negative to the gradient.
لذا، فهذه هي القيمة، وهي قيمة سالبة بالنسبة لمعامل التدرج.
Now for the final example, we have four awesomes, one awful,
والآن، بالنسبة للمثال الأخير، فإن لدينا أربعة من الأشياء الرائعة، وشيء واحد سيئ،
so four is h1(x), is a positive example so the indicator has value one.
لذا، فإن (h1(x يساوي 4، بما أن هذا مثالًا إيجابيًا، فإن المؤشر سيساوي القيمة 1.
And the probability the model thinks it's positive is 0.88.
وستكون نسبة احتمالية أن يشير النموذج إلى الإيجابية هي 0.88.
So the contribution here is four.
لذا فإن القيمة هنا هي 4.
That multiplies 1- 0.88, which is 0.12 times 4 is 0.48.
مضروبة في (0.88 - 1)، والتي تساوي 0.48.
Great, and so the total derivative
رائع، لذا فإن المجموع الكلي للمشتقة
is just going to be the sum of each one of these contributions added up together.
سيكون مجموع كل واحدة من هذه القيم مضافة معًا.
So, the derivative of l computed at wt,
وبالتالي، فإن مشتقة l محسوبة بنسبة wt
with respect to the parameter w1.
فيما يتعلق بالمعلمة W1.
It's just going to be the sum of these four contributions.
ستكون مساوية لمجموع هذه القيم الأربع.
So 1+0-0.15+0.48 which is equal
لذا، ستكون 0.48 + 0.15 - 0 + 1
to if you add it all together 1.33.
والتي تساوي إذا قمت بجمعهم معًا 1.33.
And now I'm going to do a little change of colors transformation here,
والآن، سأقوم ببعض التغييرات في تبديل الألوان هنا،
let's go to a color.
لننتقل إلى لون.
Let's write the update rule for the parameter w1.
دعونا نكتب قاعدة التحديث للمعلمة w1.
We computed this derivative, let's do the update.
لقد قمنا بحساب المشتقة، فدعونا نقم بالتحديث.
So w1 at the next iteration, iteration t+1,
لذا، فإن المعلمة w1 في التكرار التالي، وهو التكرار t+1
is going to be equal to w1 at iteration t.
ستكون مساوية للمعلمة w1 بالتكرار t.
Plus eta, the step size that multiplies
مجموعة مع المقدار η، وهو حجم الخطوة
the derivative of the likelihood function,
مضروبًا في مشتقة الدالة الاحتمالية،
at wt, with respect to the parameter w1.
wt، فيما يتعلق بالمعلمة w1.
Which is the one that we're updating here.
وهي القيمة التي نحاول تحديثها.
Now let's suppose we set eta to be 0.1.
والآن، لنفترض أننا قمنا بتعيين المقدار η ليصبح 0.1.
It's a bit of a large number.
وهو جزء قليل بالنسبة لرقم كبير.
But it makes our updates here a little simple.
ولكنه يجعل التحديثات التي نجريها هنا بسيطة بعض الشيء.
So what does this update rule says?
لذا، ماذا تقول قاعدة التحديث هذه؟
w1 at iteration t + 1 is w1 iteration t,
أن المعلمة w1 بالتكرار t هي نفس المعلمة w1 بالتكرار t+1 والتي تساوي 1.
which was 1 + eta 0.1.
مجموعة على المقدار η 0.1.
That multiplies the derivative we just computed right here,
مضروبًا في المشتقة التي قد قمنا بحسابها والتي تساوي 1.33
1.33, which means that the new parameter is going to be equal to 1.133.
والذي يعني أن المعلمة الجديدة ستساوي 1.133.
We just made our parameter a little bit bigger, which is great.
نحن فقط جعلنا المعلمة لدينا أكبر قليلًا، وهو أمر عظيم.
[MUSIC]
[موسيقى]